[Music]
foreign
repeatedly my videos and books is best
available balance of evidence
what does that mean when making
decisions is life or death important as
to what to best feed ourselves and our
families it matters less what a single
study says but rather what the totality
of peer-reviewed science has to say
individual studies can lead to headlines
like this
to know if there's really a link between
secondhand smoke and lung cancer it
would be better to look at a review of
or meta-analysis that compiles multiple
studies together the problem is that
some reviews say one thing breathing
other people's tobacco smoke is a cause
of lung cancer and some reviews say
another they're saying the effects of
secondhand smoke are insignificant and
further such talk May Foster irrational
fears and hey while we're at it you can
even directly smoke four or five
cigarettes a day and not really worry
about it so light up
why do review articles on the health
effects reach such different conclusions
well as you can imagine about 90 of
reviews written by tobacco industry
affiliate researchers said it was not
harmful whereas you get the exact
opposite number with independent reviews
written by tobacco researchers had 88
times the odds of a concluding
secondhand smoke was harmless it was all
part of their deliberate corporate
strategy to discredit the science to in
other words develop and widely publicize
evidence that secondhand smoke is
harmless
okay well can't you just stick to the
independent reviews the problem is that
industry-funded researchers have all
sorts of sneaky ways to get out
declaring conflicts of interest so it's
hard to follow the money look but even
without knowing who funded what the
majority of reviews still concluded
secondhand smoke was harmful so just
like a single study it may not be as
helpful as looking at a compilation of
studies on a topic a single review may
not be as useful as a compilation of
reviews so looking at a review of
reviews like this one it can give you a
better sense of where the best available
balance of evidence May lie
in this case it's probably best not to
inhale
wouldn't it be cool if there were
reviews of reviews for different foods
voila an exhaustive review of
meta-analysis and systematic reviews on
the associations between food and
beverage groups and major diet related
chronic diseases let's start with the
beverages
the findings were classified into three
categories protective neutral or
deleterious first up tea versus coffee
in both cases most reviews for whichever
condition they were studying found both
beverages to be protective but you can
see how this supports my recommendation
for tea over coffee every cup of coffee
is a lost opportunity to drink something
even healthier a cup of green tea
no surprise soda sinks to the bottom but
still 14 of reviews mentioned protective
effects of drinking soda well most were
references to papers like this a
cross-sectional study that found that
8th grade girls who drank more soda were
skinnier than girls who drank less okay
but this was just a snapshot in time
what do you think is more likely that
the fatter girls were heavier because
they drink less soda or that they drank
less sugary soda because they were
heavier right soda abstention May
therefore be a consequence
of obesity rather than the cause yet it
gets marked down as protective right as
a protective Association study design
flaws may also account for these wine
numbers right this review of reviews was
published back in 2014 before the
Revolution and our understanding of the
evaporating health benefits of alcohol
suggesting that the presumed health
benefits from you know moderate alcohol
may have finally collapsed thanks to in
part to a systematic error of
misclassifying former drinkers as if
they were lifelong abstainers as I
revealed in a deep dive in my latest
video series on the subject
sometimes there are unexplainable
associations so for example one of the
soft drink studies found that increased
soda consumption was associated with
lower risk of a certain type of
esophageal cancer
don't don't tell me the review was
funded by Coca-Cola the review was
funded by Coca-Cola
does that help explain these positive
milk studies I mean were they all just
funded by the dairy Council right even
more conflicts of interest have been
found among milk studies than soda
studies with industry-funded studies of
all such beverages approximately four to
eight times more likely to be favorable
to the financial interests of the study
sponsor
funding bias aside though there could be
you know legitimate reasons for the
protective effects associated with milk
consumption after all those who drink
more milk as a beverage May drink less
soda which is even worse so they come
out ahead
but it may be more than just relative
benefits the soda cancer link seems a
little tenuous not just because the code
connection but it's you know hard to
imagine a biologically plausible
mechanism whereas you know even
something as universally condemned as
tobacco isn't universally bad right as
I've explored before more than 50
Studies have consistently found a
protective association with Parkinson's
thanks to nicotine even second hand
smoke may be protected of course you
still want to avoid it may decrease risk
of Parkinson's but increases the risk of
an even deadlier brain disease stroke
not dementia lung cancer and heart
disease
which has killed off millions of
Americans since the first surgeon
general's report was released thankfully
by eating certain vegetables we may be
able to get some of the benefits without
the risk and the same may be true of
dairy as I've described before the
consumption of milk is associated with
increased risk of prostate cancer
leading to you know recommendations
suggesting men may want to cut down or
minimize their intake but milk
consumption is associated with decreased
colorectal cancer risk this appears to
be a calcium effect thankfully we may be
able to get you know the Best of Both
Worlds by eating high calcium plant
foods such as you know Greens and Beans
what does our review of reviews a study
conclude about such plant-based Foods in
comparison to animal-based Foods we'll
find out next
[Music]
thank you